Guide to the New-York Historical Society Management Committee Records 1804-1938 NYHS-RG 1
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. Official Papers, 1805-1938; 10.6 Linear feet
  - Official Papers. 1870 (4 of 4). Bryant Discourse on G.C. Verplanck., 1870 May (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Includes tickets and other documents concerning William Cullen Bryant's discourse on Gulian C. Verplanck at Steinway Hall.
  - Official Papers. 1871 (1 of 3). (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Official Papers. 1871 (2 of 3). (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Official Papers. 1871 (3 of 3)., 1869, 1871 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Includes pages from the October 9, 1869, publication The Academy.
  - Official Papers. 1872 (1 of 6). (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Official Papers. 1872 (2 of 6). (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Includes correspondence related to objections raised by the Society to the memorial to Mr. Motley, written by John Jay and read at the June meeting by John Austin Stevens.
  - Official Papers. 1872 (3 of 6). (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Official Papers. 1872 (4 of 6). Henry B. Dawson Matter. (Box 10, Folder 11)
    This folder and the next includes correspondence, affidavits, newspaper clippings, notes, meeting extracts, and other documents related to Henry B. Dawson's purported membership in N-YHS, his proposed by-law amendment, and his related lawsuit.
  - Official Papers. 1872 (5 of 6). Henry B. Dawson Matter. (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Official Papers. 1872 (6 of 6). Buckingham Smith Acquisition, 1870-1872 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    Includes correspondence, purchase receipt, resolutions, inventory of volumes, object descriptive notes, and other documents concerning the acquisition of a globe and books from the estate of Buckingham Smith. The documents in this folder were found in 2016 in the manuscript collection of Buckingham Smith papers and were moved to the N-YHS institutional archive, which was their likely original location in large part. A few of the documents do not bear directly on the acquisition, including a statement from Bellevue Hospital concerning Smith's death.
  - Official Papers. 1873 (1 of 7). (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Official Papers. 1873 (2 of 7). (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Official Papers. 1873 (3 of 7). (Box 10, Folder 16)
    Includes the memorial of Hickson W. Field.
  - Official Papers. 1873 (4 of 7). (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Official Papers. 1873 (5 of 7). (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Official Papers. 1873 (6 of 7). (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Includes the memorials of John Romeyn Brodhead, John A. Parker, and Thomas Ward.
  - Official Papers. 1873 (7 of 7). Thomas W.C. Moore Collection. (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Includes documents related to the bequest to N-YHS of autograph letters and paintings from Thomas W.C. Moore. The documents include an inventory of Moore's paintings with what appears to be Moore's own remarks on the circumstances of his acquisitions of each. The inventory includes 77 paintings, only fifteen of which were bequeathed to N-YHS; two others are noted as having been presented to N-YHS in October 1857.
  - Official Papers. 1874 (1 of 4). (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Official Papers. 1874 (2 of 4). (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Includes the memorials of Millard Fillmore and Charles Sumner.
  - Official Papers. 1874 (3 of 4). (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Official Papers. 1874 (4 of 4). (Box 11, Folder 8)
    Includes N-YHS's petition to the Common Council that the pre-1831 manuscript originals of the Council minutes be printed; remarks and resolutions on the occasion of William Cullen Bryant's 80th birthday; and attendance record of the Executive Committee members for September 1872-March 1874.
  - Official Papers. 1875 (1 of 3)., 1874-1875 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Includes the memorial of Jonathan Sturges. Includes the catalogue of items presented to N-YHS by Cyrus Curtiss on March 2, 1875.
  - Official Papers. 1875 (2 of 3). (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Official Papers. 1875 (3 of 3). (Box 11, Folder 11)
    Includes the report of the committee concerned with plans for celebrating the Centennial Anniversary of American Independence in 1876.
  - Official Papers. 1876 (1 of 4). (Box 11, Folder 12)
    Includes the memorials of Prosper M. Wetmore, Peter Cooper, and Solomon Alofsen(?).
  - Official Papers. 1876 (2 of 4). Centennial Memorials. (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Official Papers. 1876 (3 of 4). Steam Heating for Building. (Box 11, Folder 14)
    This folder includes correspondence, print matter, and cost estimates received in connection with the possibility of installing steam heat in the N-YHS building. The project was not pursued at the time.
  - Official Papers. 1876 (4 of 4). Steam Heating for Building. (Box 11, Folder 15)
    This oversize folder includes one document: a plan drawn by engineers Baker Smith & Co. of the three floors of the N-YHS building. Although it emphasizes the placement of the steam heating facilities, it also includes some other details, such as room names and dimensions.
  - Official Papers. 1871-1876. Bills and Accounts. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Official Papers. 1877 (1 of 4)., 1876-1877 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Includes the final report of the subscribers and expenses of the 1876 Celebration of the Battle of Harlem Plains. Includes a letter from E. Ellery Anderson and a report from the Librarian concerning the donation of 392 Egyptian and other objects.
  - Official Papers. 1877 (2 of 4). (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Official Papers. 1877 (3 of 4). (Box 12, Folder 4)
    Includes the memorial of John Lathrop Motley by John Jay.
  - Official Papers. 1877 (4 of 4). (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Includes the memorial of James William Beekman, remarks by the N-YHS president acknowledging the donation by George Clinton Tallmadge of the portrait of Governor George Clinton by Ezra Hines, the remarks of the Librarian on his resignation, and drafts of N-YHS's protest to the New York State legislature concerning the proposed suspension of publication of colonial records.
  - Official Papers. 1878 (1 of 3). (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Official Papers. 1878 (2 of 3). (Box 12, Folder 7)
    Includes the memorials of Willian Cullen Bryant, Edward Satterlee and Joseph Henry. Includes the Librarian's comments on the discovery of pieces of the statue of George III formerly in Bowling Green and recently purchased for N-YHS.
  - Official Papers. 1878 (3 of 3). (Box 12, Folder 8)
    Includes the list of individuals invited to the William Cullen Bryant commemoration. Includes the list of subscribers for the purchase of two paintings: A.B. Durand portrait of Col. Aaron Ogden and Charles C. Ingham portrait of Gulian C. Verplanck.
  - Official Papers. 1879 (1 of 3). (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Official Papers. 1879 (2 of 3). (Box 12, Folder 10)
    Includes the memorial of Governor John A. Dix.
  - Official Papers. 1879 (3 of 3). (Box 12, Folder 11)
    Includes the memorial of Benjamin Winthrop.
  - Official Papers. 1880 (1 of 4). (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Official Papers. 1880 (2 of 4). (Box 12, Folder 13)
    Includes a memorial of Joel Munsell.
  - Official Papers. 1880 (3 of 4). (Box 12, Folder 14)
    Includes the memorial of Erastus C. Benedict by George F. Betts (manuscript version of piece noted as printed in Magazine of American History for January 1881) and the report of the committee formed to select an artist (Daniel Huntington) for a portrait of the late John A. Dix.
  - Official Papers. 1880 (4 of 4). General Committee., 1880-[1882?] (Box 12, Folder 15)
    Includes documents related to the committee formed in March 1880 to consider the future of N-YHS, especially in terms of a new building, an endowment, a Publication Fund, and other long-term matters. Invitations and responses to an October meeting and minutes of meetings are included. One summary document refers to related events out to June 1882.
  - Official Papers. 1881 (1 of 3). (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Includes draft of a circular to members concerning membership privileges and related matters. Includes subscriptions for rearrangement of the Abbott Egyptian collection in new cases and into the principal gallery for better lighting and exhibition.
  - Official Papers. 1881 (2 of 3). (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Official Papers. 1881 (3 of 3). (Box 13, Folder 3)
    Includes documents concerning N-YHS's 77th anniversary celebration at which Andrew D. White spoke.
  - Official Papers. 1882 (1 of 4). (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Includes a circular to members concerning membership privileges and related matters.
  - Official Papers. 1882 (2 of 4). (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Includes one of the two reports submitted by the Committee on Publications to the Executive Committee in April 1882 assessing the operation of the Publication Fund.
  - Official Papers. 1882 (3 of 4). (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Official Papers. 1882 (4 of 4). Fine Arts Committee, Durr Bequest. (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Official Papers. 1883 (1 of 6). (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Official Papers. 1883 (2 of 6). (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Official Papers. 1883 (3 of 6). Evacuation Day Centennial /N-YHS 79th Anniversary. General. (Box 13, Folder 10)
    This folder and the next three includes documents related to the celebration of the Evacuation Day centennial (November 26th parade) and of N-YHS's 79th anniversary (November 27 address by John Jay at the Academy of Music on "The Peace Negotiations of 1783.") This first folder includes special committee documents, remarks, and other general material about the events.
  - Official Papers. 1883 (4 of 6). Evacuation Day Centennial /N-YHS 79th Anniversary. Invitations. (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Official Papers. 1883 (5 of 6). Evacuation Day Centennial /N-YHS 79th Anniversary. Ticket Requests. (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Official Papers. 1883 (6 of 6). Evacuation Day Centennial /N-YHS 79th Anniversary. Tickets. (Box 13, Folder 13)
    Includes tickets for the 79th anniversary event and ribbons, presumably worn during the Evacuation Day parade.
  - Official Papers. 1884 (1 of 3). (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Includes the Executive Committee attendance record for March 6, 1877, to January 1, 1884.
  - Official Papers. 1884 (2 of 3). (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Official Papers. 1884 (3 of 3). (Box 14, Folder 3)
    Includes the memorial of Charles Fenno Hoffman.
  - Official Papers. 1885 (1 of 4). (Box 14, Folder 4)
    Includes print versions of the annual report for 1884 (printed 1885) and a related circular to members. Includes a petition to the New York State Legislature proposing that it propose to the federal government a national celebration in March 1889 of the centennial anniversary of the inauguration of the U.S. government under the Constitution.
  - Official Papers. 1885 (2 of 4). (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Official Papers. 1885 (3 of 4). (Box 14, Folder 6)
    Includes a circular for soliciting subscriptions for a new building.
  - Official Papers. 1885 (4 of 4). Delegation to the Public Obsequies for General Grant. (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Official Papers. 1886 (1 of 4). (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Official Papers. 1886 (2 of 4). (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Official Papers. 1886 (3 of 4). (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Official Papers. 1886 (4 of 4). Bequests. (Box 14, Folder 11)
    The folder includes documents related to two bequests. The first includes the legal documents by which Austin Abbott, the executor of the estate of A. Ogden Butler, directed Butler's cash bequest to N-YHS; these papers include Abbott's final accounting of the estate, dating from 1874-1886. The second includes an extract of the will of Gustavus Seyffarth documenting his bequest of published works concerning Egyptian manuscripts.
  - Official Papers. 1887 (1 of 3). (Box 14, Folder 12)
    Includes remarks of the Librarian concerning the donations of a portrait by Daniel Huntington of Benjamin H. Field and a bust by Franklin Timmons(?) of Samuel Osgood.
  - Official Papers. 1887 (2 of 3). (Box 14, Folder 13)
    Includes the N-YHS appeal for funds to meet a conditional matching gift toward the erection of a new building.
  - Official Papers. 1887 (3 of 3). Washington Inauguration Centennial. (Box 14, Folder 14)
    Includes resolutions and other documents related to the initiation of plans to celebrate the centennial of George Washington's inauguration as president in April 1889. One of these resolutions is from the Sons of the Revolution.
  - Official Papers. 1888 (1 of 4). (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Official Papers. 1888 (2 of 4). (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Official Papers. 1888 (3 of 4). (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Official Papers. 1888 (4 of 4). Publication Fund. (Box 14, Folder 18)
    Includes documents related to the committee formed to consider ways and means for the regular issue of volumes of the Publication Fund.
  - Official Papers. 1889 (1 of 3). (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Official Papers. 1889 (2 of 3). (Box 15, Folder 2)
    Includes a copy of the legislative act permitting the sale of the N-YHS 2nd Avenue building and site under certain conditions, while exempting from sale any new building that might be erected, and related correspondence from Senator George F. Langbein to N-YHS President John A. King and from King to Governor David B. Hill.
  - Official Papers. 1889 (3 of 3). Oversize Item. (Box OS-1, Folder 7)
    Includes one oversize certificate from the Grand Marshal of the George Washington Inauguration Centennial celebration with an engraving of the address and images of the silver case that held the address and of the medals presented to the public schools and the Veteran Firemen's Association at the event.
  - Official Papers. 1890 (1 of 2). (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Official Papers. 1890 (2 of 2). (Box 15, Folder 4)
    Includes the memorial of member Thomas Hicks, by Committee on Fine Arts Chairman Daniel Huntington. Includes an extract relevant to N-YHS from the will of Stephen Whitney Phoenix.
  - Official Papers. 1891 (1 of 2). (Box 15, Folder 5)
    Includes notes on the Special Meeting of February 24 called to consider the acquisition of the Central Park West site for a new building. Includes the memorial of George Bancroft by N-YHS president John A. King. Includes a circular calling for subscriptions to the Publication Fund.
  - Official Papers. 1891 (2 of 2). (Box 15, Folder 6)
    Includes the report of the Special Committee on Librarian George H. Moore's resignation.
  - Official Papers. 1892 (1 of 2). (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Official Papers. 1892 (2 of 2). (Box 15, Folder 8)
    Includes a copy of the trust agreement established by Joseph F. Loubat with the trustees of Columbia College. This trust was used to fund prizes in a competition in writing in history and certain other defined fields. The trust required that successful entries be published, and a copy of the publication be given to N-YHS, among others. Also includes a list of the N-YHS delegates to a celebration of the anniversary of the Declaration of Independence at White Plains.
  - Official Papers. 1893 (1 of 3). (Box 15, Folder 9)
    Includes documents related to a proposal that New York's old city hall building be given to N-YHS for its use, after construction of a new city hall.
  - Official Papers. 1893 (2 of 3). (Box 15, Folder 10)
    Includes the memorials of Benjamin H. Field by Edward F. de Lancey, of Rev. Dr. Vermilye by Henry W. Bookstones (?), and of Hamilton Fish by John A. King.
  - Official Papers. 1893 (3 of 3). Reception for Duke of Veragua. (Box 15, Folder 11)
    Includes correspondence related to the committee of the N-YHS that formed a joint delegation with the Chamber of Commerce and the American Geographical Society to greet the Duke of Veragua as he traveled through New York on his way to the Columbian Exposition in Chicago.
  - Official Papers. 1894 (1 of 3). (Box 15, Folder 12)
    Includes notes from John A. King on the silver medals sent by Washington to the Indians in 1798, with typescripts and a copy of Rufus King correspondence of 1797-98. John King's paper was read at the January 1894 N-YHS meeting, along with a presentation of (copper?) duplicates of the medals from Rufus King's desk in Jamaica.
  - Official Papers. 1894 (2 of 3). (Box 15, Folder 13)
    Includes offer from and acceptance of contractor P. Gillings's proposal to flag the sidewalk and reset the curb at the Central Park West site, in compliance with a city ordinance.
  - Official Papers. 1894 (3 of 3). (Box 15, Folder 14)
    Includes "papers, etc. belonging to steam engine for the" N-YHS, which are various notes about a steam engine, including notes on Colden's biography of Robert Fulton. Includes the memorials of John Jay and Robert C. Winthrop by N-YHS president John A. King.
  - Official Papers. 1895 (1 of 2). (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Official Papers. 1895 (2 of 2). (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Official Papers. 1896 (1 of 2). (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Official Papers. 1896 (2 of 2). (Box 16, Folder 4)
    Includes remarks of N-YHS president at anniversary meeting.
  - Official Papers. 1897 (1 of 2). (Box 16, Folder 5)
    Includes request from the Metropolitan Street Railway Company for consent to use underground electricity for the 8th Avenue Railroad.
  - Official Papers. 1897 (2 of 2). (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Official Papers. 1898 (1 of 2). (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Official Papers. 1898 (2 of 2). William Kelby Memorial., 1898 November (Box 16, Folder 8)
    Includes the draft manuscript of John Austin Stevens's memoir of the former Librarian, William Kelby.
  - Official Papers. 1899 (1 of 2). (Box 16, Folder 9)
    Includes the memorial of long-time Recording Secretary Andrew Warner.
  - Official Papers. 1899 (2 of 2). (Box 16, Folder 10)
    Includes the memorials of members Charles Patrick Daly and Cornelius Vanderbilt.
  - Official Papers. 1900 (1 of 2). (Box 16, Folder 11)
    Includes the request of John Austin Stevens for members to contribute funds for a portrait of the late Librarian William Kelby, and the subscription lists. See also February 1901 for a note from Stevens concerning the completed portrait and disposition of surplus funds.
  - Official Papers. 1900 (2 of 2). (Box 16, Folder 12)
    Includes the memorials to N-YHS Treasurer Robert Schell by John A. King, and to King by a committee of three members.
  - Official Papers. 1901 (1 of 3). (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Official Papers. 1901 (2 of 3). (Box 16, Folder 14)
    Includes notes for a memorial to John A. Weekes, invitations and tickets to N-YHS's 97th anniversary celebration at which Charles Francis Adams spoke, the report of the Ladies Committee, and financial information, especially for the Building Fund.
  - Official Papers. 1901 (3 of 3). Building Committee. (Box 16, Folder 15)
    Includes documents related to the committee formed to raise funds for the erection of a building on the Central Park West site, including resolutions, circulars, subscription requests, a poem by J.L. Beekman, and other material.
  - Official Papers. 1902 (1 of 3). (Box 17, Folder 1)
    Includes a circular for the Publication Fund.
  - Official Papers. 1902 (2 of 3). (Box 17, Folder 2)
    Includes the memorials of Eugene Hoffman and Nicholas Fish, and the report of the Committee on Membership.
  - Official Papers. 1902 (3 of 3). Building Committee. (Box 17, Folder 3)
    Includes reports of the committee and the printed Communication to the Members of the New York Historical Society from the Building Committee, with floor plans of the projected Central Park West building.
  - Official Papers. 1903 (1 of 3). (Box 17, Folder 4)
    Includes a report by H.A. Hammond Smith with his observations concerning the conservation needs of various paintings in the collection.
  - Official Papers. 1903 (2 of 3). (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Official Papers. 1903 (3 of 3). (Box 17, Folder 6)
    Includes Recording Secretary Sydney Carney's article "Historical Societies of the United States" for the Encyclopedia Americana as provided to the N-YHS Executive Committee.
  - Official Papers. 1904 (1 of 4). (Box 17, Folder 7)
    Includes copy of letter to the New York City mayor and aldermen calling for the preservation of city records dating from the colonial period to early nineteenth century.
  - Official Papers. 1904 (2 of 4). (Box 17, Folder 8)
    Includes documents related to Henry Dexter's contributions to the construction of the Central Park West building. Includes provenance documents concerning the donation to N-YHS of the padlock and key of the "long room" of the demolished "bridewell," formerly in City Hall Park.
  - Official Papers. 1904 (3 of 4). American Numismatic & Archaeological Society. (Box 17, Folder 9)
    Includes a draft agreement for a consolidation of the American Numismatic & Archaeological Society into N-YHS, and opposition circulars from members of the Numismatic Society.
  - Official Papers. 1904 (4 of 4). N-YHS Centennial. (Box 17, Folder 10)
    Includes documents related to the celebration banquet at Delmonico's (menu, seating plan, speeches) and the commemorative medal struck for the occasion.
  - Official Papers. 1905 (1 of 3). (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Official Papers. 1905 (2 of 3). (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Official Papers. 1905 (3 of 3). New York Genealogical & Biographical Society. (Box 17, Folder 13)
    Includes draft agreements for the amalgamation of N-YHS and the New York Genealogical & Biographical Society, and two letters from William Gordon Ver Planck of the latter organization.
  - Official Papers. 1899-1905. Sydney H. Carney, Jr. Files (1 of 10)., 1899-1901 May (Box 18, Folder 1)
    Includes a subscription book for the Building Fund.
  - Official Papers. 1899-1905. Sydney H. Carney, Jr. Files (2 of 10)., 1901 June-December (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Official Papers. 1899-1905. Sydney H. Carney, Jr. Files (3 of 10)., 1902 January-April (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Official Papers. 1899-1905. Sydney H. Carney, Jr. Files (4 of 10)., 1902 May-December (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Official Papers. 1899-1905. Sydney H. Carney, Jr. Files (5 of 10)., 1903 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Official Papers. 1899-1905. Sydney H. Carney, Jr. Files (6 of 10)., 1904 January (Box 18, Folder 6)
    Includes a letter from York & Sawyer in which the architects, in response to a challenge to their bill for services, reviewed their engagement with N-YHS, particularly with respect to the need for changes in the original building plans because of unforeseen restrictions related to the neighboring house of Oscar Strauss. See also NYHS-RG 3, Series III. Central Park West Construction - Central Portion for other correspondence between Carney and Committee Chair Samuel Hoffman concerning this matter.
  - Official Papers. 1899-1905. Sydney H. Carney, Jr. Files (7 of 10)., 1904 February (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Official Papers. 1899-1905. Sydney H. Carney, Jr. Files (8 of 10)., 1904 March-December (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - (RESTRICTED). Official Papers. 1899-1905. Sydney H. Carney, Jr. Files (9 of 10)., 1904 October-November (Box 18, Folder 9)
    This folder includes fragmented documents which have restricted access because of their condition. Photocopies of the documents are in folder 8 of 10 above and those copies should be used.
  - Official Papers. 1899-1905. Sydney H. Carney, Jr. Files (10 of 10)., 1905, undated (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Official Papers. 1906 (1 of 2). (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Official Papers. 1906 (2 of 2). (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Official Papers. 1907 (1 of 3). (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Official Papers. 1907 (2 of 3). (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Official Papers. 1907 (3 of 3). 2nd Avenue Building. (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Official Papers. 1908. (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Official Papers. 1909 (1 of 2). (Box 19, Folder 1)
    Includes the booklet regarding the placement of the Hudson ship "Half Moon" window in the N-YHS Library.
  - Official Papers. 1909 (2 of 2). (Box 19, Folder 2)
    Includes N-YHS petition and eventual relief concerning an assessment and property lien for sidewalk flagging.
  - Official Papers. 1910 (1 of 2). (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Official Papers. 1910 (2 of 2). (Box 19, Folder 4)